Guide to the Dial Press Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dial Press records
1924-1983
YCAL MSS 253
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.5
(19 boxes)
The Dial Press Records contain publicity files, catalogs, photographs, and other materials that document the workings of this twentieth-century press.
Dial Press
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Donna A. Schrader, 1987.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Dial Press
Founded in 1923, the Dial Press was a distinctly separate entity from the Dial Magazine although they were housed in the same building and Scofield Thayer worked with both. Many accounts state 1924 as the founding date, but this was the year of the Press's first imprint. The Dial Press logo design was based on the signet ring of founder Lincoln MacVeagh. Early ads were headlined "At the sign of the cupid and the Lion" and later just the logo was used. Early authors included Elizabeth Bowen, W.R. Burnett and Glenway Wescott. After MacVeagh sold the Press in 1933, it was fairly inactive until 1938, when it changed ownership again. Under B.C. Hoffman, the character of the firm changed to include books of more popular appeal. In 1945, two popular titles were Gladys Schmitt's David, The King and Frank Yerby's The Foxes of Harrow. Between 1963 and 1965, the Press published several popular books, including James Baldwin's The Fire Next Time, Herbert Gold's Salt, Thomas Berger's Little Big Man, and Norman Mailer's An American Dream.
The following chronology provides dates for key events:
1923: The Dial Press was founded by Lincoln MacVeagh at 461 Park Avenue South in Manhattan. Scofield Thayer, publisher of the Dial Magazine, was the its first editor.
1933: MacVeagh sold Dial Press to Max Solap.
1938: Max Solap sold Dial Press to B.C. Hoffman.
1961: Dial Press Books for Young Readers was created.
1963: Dell Publishing Company acquired 60% of the Dial Press stock but the Press remained an independent subsidiary.
1964: Dial Press moved to 750 Third Avenue.
1969: The Dial Press became wholly owned by Dell Publishing Company.
1973: Dial Press made another move to Dag Hammarskjold Plaza.
1976: Doubleday bought Dell Publishing.
1985: Doubleday dissolved Dial Press on April 16.
Description of the Papers
The Dial Press Records document the workings of this twentieth-century press and consist primarily of publicity files. Author biographies, bibliographies, and book synopses reveal the way in which Dial Press publicized its authors and titles. Also included are catalogs listing all Dial Press publications. The Records span the years 1924 to 1984.
Arrangement
The Dial Press Records are organized into two Series: Publicity Files and Catalogs.
American fiction -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Publishers and publishing; Baldwin, James, 1924-1987; Bourjaily, Vance, 1922-2010; Brokhin, Yuri, 1934-; Brown, Raphael, 1912-; Cohen, Jerry S., 1925-; Condon, Richard, 1915-1996; Gaines, Ernest J., 1933-; Gold, Herbert, 1924-; Lester, Julius, 1939-2018; Ludlum, Robert, 1927-2001; MacVeagh, Lincoln, 1890-1972; Mailer, Norman, 1923-2007; Marty, Martin E., 1928-; Mintz, Morton, 1922-; Thayer, Scofield, 1889-1982; Yerby, Frank, 1916-1991; Dell Publishing Company; Dial Books for Young Readers; Dial Press
- Publicity Files, 1924-1983; Series I; 7.5; (15 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into five subseries: General Publicity Files; Author Biography Files; Index Cards; Photographs and Slides; and Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  General Publicity Files consists of biographies, bibliographies, book synopses, and ephemera used in book jackets, press releases and in disseminating information to press, libraries, and bookstores. The files document publications for each year between 1951 and 1983 and the files for most years begin with a typescript list of published titles and prices.
  Author Biography Files contains brief biographies of Dial Press authors that were used as sources for publicity information.
  Index Cards consists of three card indices to Dial Press publications. The first indexes, by author, pre-1962 titles stored in a warehouse; each card contains only author, title, date, and warehouse location. The second is a title index, 1962-1982, which lists the author, price, and publication date, and for some titles also includes information about the editor, agent, serial rights, illustrations, and contents. The third index, "Special Authors," contains cards for a small selection of authors such as James Baldwin, Robert Ludlum, and Norman Mailer, which seem to have been culled from the title index.
  Other Papers includes documentation of author publication receptions and publicity tours, Dial Press logo samples and stamp, guest books, stationery, and reviews of Dial Press titles. Of particular interest is a collection of correspondence and printed materials documenting the history of the Dial Press.
  - General Publicity Files, 1924-1983
    General Publicity Files is arranged chronologically. The bulk of the material was originally housed in three-ring binders, arranged by year and then alphabetically by author. The binders were disassembled during processing but the foldered files remain in original order.
    - 1951-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
    - 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15-22)
    - 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 23-28)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 29-34)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 35-42)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 6, Folder 43-48)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 49-54)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 55-60)
    - 1983 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Author Biography Files, 1961-1983
    - A-O, circa 1961-1983 (Box 9, Folder 62-70)
    - P-Z, circa 1961-1983 (Box 10, Folder 71-73)
    - Baldwin, James, 1971-1979 (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Bourjaily, Vance, 1970-1982 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Brokhin, Yuri, 1981-1983 (Box 10, Folder 76-77)
      Includes printed material regarding Brokhin's 1983 murder
    - Condon, Richard, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Gaines, Ernest J., 1967-1983 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Ludlum, Robert, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Yerby, Frank, 1979, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Index cards, Before 1962-1980
    - "Old Dial Books, Filed By Author, Stored in Warehouse", Before 1962 (Box 11)
    - "Dial titles filed by title", 1962-1982 (Box 12)
    - "Special Authors" index, 1958-1980 (Box 13, Folder 82-83)
  - Photographs and slides, circa 1970, undated
    - Slides of various publicity materials, undated (Box 13, Folder 84-85)
    - Photographs, circa 1970, undated
      Photographs of James Baldwin, H. Rap Brown, Robert Condon, Herbert Gold, Julius Lester, and Frank Yerby
  - Other Papers, 1924-1980, undated
    Other Papers is chiefly arranged by material format and then alphabetically or chronologically within each format group.
    - Dial Press logo
      - Dial Press logo, printed materials, undated (Box 13, Folder 86)
      - Dial Press logo stamp, undated (Box 13, Folder 87)
    - History of Dial Press, correspondence and printed materials, 1924-1983 (Box 13, Folder 88-90)
    - Guest book, 1965, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 91)
    - Guest book, 1966-1982 (Box 13, Folder 92)
    - Blank invitations for author publication receptions and Dial Press holiday cards, 1966-1980 (Box 14, Folder 93)
    - Publicity stationery, undated (Box 14, Folder 94)
    - Oh, Promised Land by James Street, publicity announcement, 1940 (Box 14, Folder 95)
    - Publisher's Weekly Volume 148 Number 24 December 1946 (Box 14, Folder 96)
      Includes Dial Press titles
    - Dial Souvenir Sampler, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 97)
    - National Book Award certificate to Martin E. Marty for Righteous Empire, 1972
    - Book reviews, 1963-1974
      - Baldwin, James, The Fire Next Time, 1963
      - Baldwin, James, If Beale Street Could Talk, 1974
      - Baldwin, James, Little Man, Little Man, 1977
      - Condon, Richard, Mile High, 1969
      - Mintz, Morton and Jerry S. Cohen, America, Inc.: Who Owns and Operates the United States, 1971
- Catalogs, 1924-1983; Series II; 1.38; (4 boxes)
  Catalogs are arranged chronologically under headings for each publication series.
  This series contains catalogs listing the Dial Press Adult Books and Books for Young Readers publications.
  - Dial Press Adult Books and Books for Young Readers
    - 1924-1949 (Box 15, Folder 98-104)
      1924 catalog is a photocopy
    - 1949-1966 (Box 16, Folder 105-108)
    - 1966-1979 (Box 17, Folder 109-114)
    - 1979-1983 (Box 18, Folder 115-117)
  - Dial Press Books for Young Readers
    - 1953-1982, undated posters (Box 18, Folder 118-120)
- Oversize
  - Photographs (Series I), circa 1970, undated (Box 19, Folder 121-123)
  - National Book Award certificate to Martin E. Marty for Righteous Empire (Series I), 1972 (Box 19, Folder 124)
  - Book review: Baldwin, James, The Fire Next Time (Series I), 1963 (Box 19, Folder 125)
  - Book review: Baldwin, James, If Beale Street Could Talk (Series I), 1974 (Box 19, Folder 126)
  - Book review: Baldwin, James, Little Man, Little Man (Series I), 1977 (Box 19, Folder 126a)
  - Book review: Condon, Richard, Mile High (Series I), 1969 (Box 19, Folder 127)
  - Book review: Mintz, Morton and Jerry S. Cohen, America, Inc.: Who Owns and Operates the United States (Series I), 1971 (Box 19, Folder 128)